Register of the Burnett Bolloten Papers, 1923-1991
Hoover Institution Archives
Burnett Bolloten Papers,
1923-1991
46002
Hoover Institution Archives
117 manuscript boxes, 5 oversize boxes, 266 microfilm reels, 1 envelope, 2 phonotape reels, 5 phonotape cassettes (96.2 linear feet)
Writings, correspondence, serial issues, clippings, other printed matter, and audiovisual materials, relating to political, military and international aspects of the Spanish Civil War. Includes clippings from the Spanish, French, Italian and British press arranged day-by-day, microfilm of Spanish and foreign periodical issues, and copies of papers of Luis Araquistain, relating to the war. Used as research material for the books by Burnett Bolloten, The Grand Camouflage (1961), The Spanish Revolution (1979), and The Spanish Civil War (1991).
Bolloten, Burnett, 1909-1987
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1946.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
1909, June 24 Born, Bangor, Wales
1936-1938 Reporter, United Press International, Spain
1961 Author, The Grand Camouflage
1979 Author, The Spanish Revolution
1987, October 27 Died, Sunnyvale, California
1991 Author, The Spanish Civil War: Revolution and Counterrevolution (published posthumously)
Araquistain, Luis, 1886-1959; Companys y Jover, Luis, 1882-1940; Duque, Jose; Lamoneda, Ramon; Negrin, Juan, 1889-; Prieto, Indalecio; Rio, Ricardo del; Schwartzmann, Manuel; Spain--Politics and government--1931-1939; Vidal, Miguel; Agriculture--Spain.; Aragon--History.; Catalonia--History.; Journalists.; Phonotapes.; Spain--Economic conditions--1918-1975.; Spain--History--Civil War, 1936-1939.; Spain.
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1987. (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Clippings, letters, and eulogies. Arranged chronologically.
  - Clippings, letters, and eulogies, 1987. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1936-1991 (Box 1-4)
  Mimeographs and typescripts, dispatches, bibliography, notes, and correspondence. Arranged chronologically.
  - General
    - Bibliography, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Comments by Diego Abad de Santillan relating to Bolloten's research, 1965 (Folder 3)
    - Dispatches from Spain, 1936 May-1937 July (Folder 4)
    - Notes and draft fragments (Folder 5-7)
  - "Anarchists in Government: A Paradox of the Spanish Civil War, " n.d. (co-authored with George Esenwein). Typescript, 1936-1939 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - The Spanish Revolution, Typescript, 1979. (Folder 2-3)
  - "Reply to Professor Robert Skidolsky's Article in Encounter of " 1980 May 10. Typescript and correspondence with Melvin Lasky, 1981, June 1980 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - The Spanish Civil War: Revolution and Counterrevolution, Mimeograph, 1991.
    - Chapters 1-31 (Folder 2-3)
    - Chapters 32-65 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
- CORRESPONDENCE FILE, 1928-1987 (Box 5-7)
  Includes writings and correspondence by others. Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - General, 1936-1985 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Abad de Santillan, Diego, 1946-1972 (Folder 2)
  - Alcon, Marcos, 1948-1950 (Folder 3)
  - Amiama, Gabriel ( Carta del ESTE), 1980 (Folder 4)
  - Araquistain, Luis, 1947-1949 (Folder 5)
  - Arquer, Jordi, Includes correspondence with others, 1948-1981. (Folder 6-7)
  - Asensio, Jose, 1948-1949 (Folder 8)
  - Balius, Jaime, 1946-1949 (Folder 9)
  - Barea, Arturo and Ilsa, 1950 (Folder 10)
  - Bates, Ralph, 1940 (Folder 11)
  - Blazquez, Martin, 1949-1950 (Folder 12)
  - Bullejos, Jose, 1949-1951 (Folder 13)
  - Campos, Severino, 1950 (Folder 14)
  - Cardona Rosell, Mariano, 1949-1953 (Folder 15)
  - Carrillo, Wenceslao, 1951 (Folder 16)
  - Casasus, Mariano, 1981-1982 (Folder 17)
  - Castro Delgado, Enrique, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Deltell, Luis, 1949-1950 (Folder 2)
  - Editorial Etcetera, 1979-1980 (Folder 3)
  - Encounter (Melvin Lasky), 1979 (Folder 4)
  - Erickson, John, 1977-1980 (Folder 5)
  - Escribano, Antonio, 1950-1951 (Folder 6)
  - Ferrandiz Alborz, F., 1949-1953 (Folder 7)
  - Galindez, Jesus de, 1949-1952 (Folder 8)
  - Garcia Duran, Juan, 1965 (Folder 9)
  - Garcia Pradas, Jose, 1946-1950 (Folder 10)
  - Gorkin, Julian, 1946-1968 (Folder 11)
  - Grandizo Munis, Manuel, 1948-1949 (Folder 12)
  - Hernandez, Jesus, 1948-1949 (Folder 13)
  - Herrick, William, 1985-1986 (Folder 14)
  - Irujo, Andres Maria de, 1946-1952 (Folder 15)
  - Jellinek, Frank, 1944 (Folder 16)
  - Jimenez, Miguel, Includes writings by Jimenez, 1948-1949. (Folder 17)
  - Johnston, Verle B., Includes writings by Johnston, 1965-1987. (Folder 18)
  - Lehning, Arthur, 1978-1980 (Folder 19)
  - Leval, Gaston, 1949-1953 (Folder 20)
  - Liarte, Ramon, 1949 (Folder 21)
  - Library of Congress, 1967-1970 (Folder 22)
  - Luca de Tena, Juan Ignacio, 1973 (Folder 23)
  - Madariaga, Salvador, 1950 (Folder 24)
  - Malefakis, Edward, 1961-1980 (Folder 25)
  - Marshall, Herbert, 1976 (Folder 26)
  - Martinez, Cesar, 1968-1970 (Folder 27)
  - Martinez Amutio, Justo, 1982 (Folder 28)
  - Martinez Dasi, Salvador, 1949-1950 (Folder 29)
  - Mas, Valerio, 1949-1972 (Folder 30)
  - Maurin, Joaquin, Includes correspondence with Jordi Arquer, Oscar Perez Solis, Bertram Wolfe and others, 1928-1972. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Menendez de Beltran, Leonor, 1980-1984 (Folder 2)
  - Milton, Harry, Correspondence with George Kopp, Leon Trotsky and another, 1937-1939. (Folder 3)
  - Montseny, Federica, 1947-1981 (Folder 4)
  - Ogilvie-Forbes, George, 1948 (Folder 5)
  - Pearson, H. M., 1948 (Folder 6)
  - Peel, Bill, 1939? (Folder 7)
  - Peirats, Jose, 1950-1954 (Folder 8)
  - Perez Salas, Jesus, 1948-1954 (Folder 9)
  - Piera, Sebastian, Correspondence with David Wingate Pike, 1985. (Folder 10)
  - Pou, Bernardo, 1949-1950 (Folder 11)
  - Prieto, Indalecio, 1947 (Folder 12)
  - Quintana y Peia, Alfonso, 1979-1982 (Folder 13)
  - Ramiro Gutierrez, Emilio, Includes writings by Ramiro Gutierrez, 1966-1968. (Folder 14)
  - Regler, Gustav, 1946-1948 (Folder 15)
  - Rio, Ricardo del, Notes and fragments (Folder 16)
  - Rudiger, Helmut, 1949-1952 (Folder 17)
  - Saborit, Andres, 1963-1968 (Folder 18)
  - Solano, Wilebaldo, 1971-1981 (Folder 19)
  - Sorel, Andres, 1978-1982 (Folder 20)
  - Souchy, Augustin, 1950 (Folder 21)
  - Tarradellas, Jo, sep, 1971-1972 (Folder 22)
  - Thalmann, Paul, 1977 (Folder 23)
  - Usabiaga, Jean, 1950-1951 (Folder 24)
  - Villanueva, Antonio, 1945-1951 (Folder 25)
  - Viñas, Angel, 1977-1982 (Folder 26)
  - Weller, George, Includes writings by Weller and correspondence with Ella Wolfe and others, 1979-1981. (Folder 27)
  - Wolfe, Bertram, Includes correspondence with Freda Kirchwey, 1937-1942. (Folder 28)
- LUIS ARAQUISTAIN QUEVEDO FILE, 1935-1984. (Box 8-9)
  Holograph, typescript, and printed copies of writings by Araquistain, correspondence, speeches and writings by others, reports, notes, archival guide, and clippings. Arranged by form.
  Primarily photocopies of material located in the Spanish Archivo Historico Nacional
  - General. Archival guide, printed excerpts, and clippings, 1946-1984 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Speeches and writings
    - General. Official reports, 1937 (Folder 2)
    - "Una Carta al Times," Relates to political goals of Spanish exiles, particularly in the Junta Espaiola de Liberacion, based in Mexico. Holograph, 1944. (Folder 3)
    - "Carta de Luis Araquistain al presidente de las Cortes Republicanas, Diego Martinez Barrio," Printed copy, 1939 April 4. (Folder 4)
    - El Comunismo y la Guerra de Espana, Photocopy of printed pamphlet, 1939. (Folder 5)
    - "El mito de la bolchevizacion," Holograph, n.d. (Folder 6)
    - "Negrin," Holograph, 1944 November 25. (Folder 7)
    - "Negrin Held Dupe of Soviet Russia," Printed copy, n.d. (Folder 8)
    - "?Que haria hoy Largo Caballero?" Printed copy, 1949 April. (Folder 9)
    - Report of speech by Juan Negrin, Typescript, n.d. (Folder 10)
    - Review? Relates to the role of the Soviet Union in Spain, Holograph, n.d. (Folder 11)
    - Review of Die Beziehungen Zwischen Deutschland und der Sowjetunion, 1939-1941, Holograph (Folder 12)
    - Review of Traslado del oro espanol a Rusia, Holograph, n.d. (Folder 13)
    - Reviews of Freedom's Battle and The Last Optimist by Julio Alvarez del Vayo, Holograph (Folder 14)
    - "Rusia y Espaia," El Socialista, Holograph outline and printed copy, 1950 August 10. (Folder 15)
    - "Los Rusos en Espaia," Holograph, n.d. (Folder 16)
    - "Russian Action in Spanish War Now Revealed," ? Printed copy, 1939 June 11 (Folder 17)
    - "Siglos de Historia en un Aio," Claridad, Printed copy, 1937 April 6. (Folder 18)
    - "Soviet Activity in Spain Shown," Printed copy, n.d. (Folder 19)
    - "Soviet Chief Sends Advice to Caballero," Printed copy, 1939. (Folder 20)
    - "Soviets Broke Caballero, Prieto to Grab Control of Loyalists, War Depts.," The New Leader, Printed copy, n.d. (Folder 21)
    - Statement, Relates to relocation of Spanish government from Madrid. Typescript, 1936 November 7. (Folder 22)
    - Statement on the May events in Barcelona, Typescript, 1937. (Folder 23)
    - Correspondence
      - General. Official dispatches from the Spanish Embassy in Paris, 1936-1937 (Folder 32)
      - Aguirre, Jose Maria de, 1937 (Folder 33)
      - Alvarez del Vayo, Julio, 1936-1937 (Folder 34)
      - Asensio, Jose, 1936 (Folder 35)
      - Azcarate, Pablo, 1936-1937 (Folder 36)
      - Banque Commerciale pour L'Europe du Nord, 1937 (Folder 37)
      - Baraibar, Carlos de, 1936-1937 (Folder 38)
      - Bullejos, Jose, 1944 (Folder 39)
      - Carrillo, Wenceslao, 1937-1940 (Folder 40)
      - Chapiro, Jose, 1937-1938 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Domingo, Marcelino, 1936-1937 (Folder 2)
      - Espla, Carlos, 1937 (Folder 3)
      - Falcon, Cesar, 1942 (Folder 4)
      - Galarza, Angel, 1939 (Folder 5)
      - Garcia Pradas, Jose, 1940 (Folder 6)
      - Gonzalez Peia, Ramon, 1939 (Folder 7)
      - Hemingway, Ernest, 1937 (Folder 8)
      - Hernandez Zancajo, Carlos, 1939 (Folder 9)
      - L'Humanite, 1937 (Folder 10)
      - Irujo y Ollo, Manuel de, Includes letters by Julio Alvarez del Vayo and Indalecio Prieto, 1937-1941. (Folder 11)
      - Johnson, Hewlett, 1937 (Folder 12)
      - Koestler, Arthur, n.d. (Folder 13)
      - Krivitsky, W. G., 1939 (Folder 14)
      - Lamoneda, Ramon, 1937-1939 (Folder 15)
      - Largo Caballero, Francisco, 1936-1945 (Folder 16)
      - Llopis, Rodolfo, 1940-1946 (Folder 17)
      - Martinez Barrio, Diego, 1937 (Folder 18)
      - Mendez, Rafael, 1958-1959 (Folder 19)
      - Miaja Menant, Jose, 1937 (Folder 20)
      - Montseny, Federica, 1937 (Folder 21)
      - Negrin, Juan, 1937-1944 (Folder 22)
      - Nin, Andres, 1935-1936 (Folder 23)
      - Ortega y Gasset, Eduardo, 1937 (Folder 24)
      - Ossorio y Gallardo, Angel, 1937 (Folder 25)
      - Palencia, Isabel, 1936? (Folder 26)
      - Pascua, Marcelino, 1937 (Folder 27)
      - Pollitt, Harry, 1936 (Folder 28)
      - Pra, Pedro, 1937 (Folder 29)
      - Prieto, Indalecio, 1937-1946 (Folder 30)
      - Rivas Cherif, Cipriano de, 1936-1938 (Folder 31)
      - Roces, W., 1936-1937 (Folder 32)
      - Rojo, Vicente, 1939 (Folder 33)
      - Romero Solano, Luis, 1939 (Folder 34)
      - Rubio Hidalgo, Luis, 1937 (Folder 35)
      - Saborit, Andres, 1949 (Folder 36)
      - Sanchez Albornoz, Claudio, 1936 (Folder 37)
      - Southworth, H. R., 1959 (Folder 38)
      - Tomas, Pascual, 1939 (Folder 39)
      - Union de Banques Suisses, 1955 (Folder 40)
      - Val, Eduardo, n.d. (Folder 41)
      - Vazquez Rodriguez, Mariano (Marianet), n.d. (Folder 42)
      - Vidiella, Rafael, 1937 (Folder 43)
      - Zabalza, Ricardo, 1937 (Folder 44)
    - "Los sucesos de Barcelona y la embajada de Espaia en Paris," Holograph, 1937 May. (Folder 24)
    - Untitled fragment relating to Russian involvement in the Spanish Civil War, Holograph, n.d. (Folder 25)
    - Untitled writing relating to Juan Negrin, Holograph, n.d. (Folder 26)
    - Untitled writing relating to the role of Spanish communists in the Spanish Civil War, Holograph, n.d. (Folder 27)
    - Untitled writings on the origins of the Spanish Civil War, Holographs, n.d. (Folder 28)
    - "La Verdad Sobre el Comunismo en Espaia," Open letter to Norman Thomas. Typescripts, 1939 January. (Folder 29)
    - "What Stalin Did With Spain," Printed copy (Folder 30)
    - "Why the Spanish Republic Fell: A Tragedy of Errors," Holograph, n.d. (Folder 31)
  - Subject file
    - General. Typescript and printed copies of speeches and writings by Jay Allen, Sam Baron, Harry Gannes and another, 1937-1939 (Folder 45)
    - Consejo Nacional de Defensa. Communication to the Diputacion Permanente de las Cortes, typescript report by Trifo Gomez, and a typescript report relating to the coup entitled "Levantamiento comunista," ca. 1937-1939, March 1939 (Folder 46)
    - Largo Caballero government, Formation of. Notes by Jose Aguirre, 1936 September 4 (Folder 47)
    - Partido Socialista Obrero Espaiol. Letters between the executive committee and Jose Aguirre, Indalecio Prieto and others, 1937-1946 (Folder 48)
    - Toryho, Jacinto. "Destitucion Fulminante del Compaiero Jacinto Toryho de su Cargo de Director de Solidaridad Obrera," Typescript report by Toryho, 1938. (Folder 49)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS BY OTHERS, 1923-1986 (Box 10-14)
  Typescripts, printed copies, notes, interviews, speeches, clippings; also includes material by others relating to these individuals. Arranged alphabetically by author.
  - Abad de Santillan, Diego. Printed writings and articles, 1937-1984 (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
  - Aigaude, Artemio. Typescript notes and interview, ca. 1946 (Folder 3)
  - Alvarez del Vayo, Julio. Printed writings, articles, speech, clippings, and interview, 1938-1980 (Folder 4)
  - Arquer, Jordi. Holograph notes, n.d. (Folder 5)
  - Asensio, Jose. Printed writing, clippings, and typescript notes by Enrique Lumen, 1938-1970 (Folder 6)
  - Barea, Arturo. Printed memoir excerpt, 1946 (Folder 7)
  - Bates, Ralph. Printed writings, clippings, interview transcript, and notes, 1936-1944 (Folder 8)
  - Beimler, Hans. Typescript copy of "Hans Beimler: Dachau-Madrid: Ein Document Unsere [sic] Zeit," (Folder 9)
  - Bejarano, Benigno ("Lazarillo de Tormes"). Printed writings and a typescript copy of "Les Morts ne Vouz Pardonnent Pas," (Folder 10)
  - Brandt, Willy. Printed copy of Krieg und Revolution in Spanien, 1937 (Folder 11)
  - Brockway, Fenner. Printed writings, 1936-1942 (Folder 12)
  - Carrillo, Santiago. Printed writings, interview excerpts, and speeches, 1937-1979 (Folder 13)
  - Carrillo, Wenceslao. Speech, printed excerpt, and notes, 1939-1946 (Folder 14)
  - Casado, Segismundo. Printed writing, 1939 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Cierva, Ricardo de la. Printed writings and printed articles, 1969-1983 (Folder 2)
  - Comorera, Juan. Printed writings, clipping, reports, and notes, 1936-1946 (Folder 3)
  - Diaz, Jose. Printed writings and printed articles, 1938-1982 (Folder 4)
  - Dominguez, Edmundo. Printed writing, 1940 (Folder 5)
  - Dos Passos, John. Printed writings and printed articles, 1937-1975 (Folder 6)
  - Ehrenburg, Ilya. Printed writings and clippings, 1936-1968 (Folder 7)
  - Fabbri, Luis. Pamphlet, and printed article by Diego Abad de Santillan, 1923-1935 (Folder 8)
  - Fabregas, Juan P. Printed writings and printed excerpt, 1937 (Folder 9)
  - Garcia Oliver, Juan. Typescript questionnaire, printed writings, printed articles, clipping, and notes, 1940-1979 (Folder 10)
  - Garcia Pradas, Jose. Printed writings and clipping, 1939-1974 (Folder 11)
  - Garcia Val, Alejandro. Typescript interview and notes, 1939 (Folder 12)
  - Gil Robles, Jose Maria. Printed writings and clippings, including articles by Juan Ignacio Luca de Tena, 1937-1980 (Folder 13)
  - Giral, Jose. Typescript interview and clipping, 1939-1963 (Folder 14)
  - Goldman, Emma. Printed writings and clippings, 1937-1986 (Folder 15)
  - Gomez, Socrates. Printed writings and printed articles, 1937-1980 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Gonzalez, Valentin. Printed writings, clippings, and printed articles and excerpts, SEE ALSO: Partido Comunista de Espaia, 1936-1977. (Folder 2)
  - Gorkin, Julian. Printed writings, printed interview, speeches, and clippings, 1939-1980 (Folder 3)
  - Hernandez, Jesus. Printed writings, clipping, speech, and mimeograph interview, 1937-1971 (Folder 4)
  - Hidalgo de Cisneros, Ignacio and Constancia de la Mora. Shorthand interview notes, clipping, and printed writings by Hidalgo de Cisneros and de la Mora, SEE ALSO: SPEECHES AND WRITINGS/General/Dispatches, 1939-1950. (Folder 5)
  - Ibarruri, Dolores. Printed writings, articles, interview, and clippings, 1937-1977 (Folder 6)
  - Koestler, Arthur. Printed writing and clippings, 1956-1981 (Folder 7)
  - Koltzov, Mikhail. Printed writings by Koltzov, bibliography, biographical sketches and notes, and printed excerpts and articles, 1957-1981 (Folder 8)
  - Largo Caballero, Francisco. Printed writings, clippings, and printed articles by Diego Abad de Santillan and others, 1925-1978 (Folder 9)
  - Leval, Gaston. Printed writings, clippings, and a typescript photocopy of "Sur L'Activite Syndicale" (incomplete), 1947-1972 (Folder 10)
  - Lister, Enrique. Printed writings, printed interview, clippings, and notes, 1937-1977 (Folder 11)
  - Lore, Ludwig. Printed writings, 1936 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Madariaga, Salvador de. Printed writings, interview, and clippings, 1942-1979 (Folder 2)
  - Marty, Andre. Printed writings and typescript excerpt by Ernest Hemingway (?), 1937 (Folder 3)
  - Maurin, Joaquin. Letters by Maurin, clippings, printed articles, typescript copy of George Esenwein, "Joaquin Maurin Julia," and writings by Maurin, including a typescript copy of "The Good Bandit,", 1936-1974 (Folder 4)
  - Mera, Cipriano. Printed writing, speech, articles, and interview, 1939-1976 (Folder 5)
  - Minor, Robert. Pamphlet entitled The Struggle Against War and the Peace Policy of the Soviet Union, 1936 (Folder 6)
  - Miravitlles, Jaume. Printed writings, including a brief article relating to Luis Companys, 1936-1963 (Folder 7)
  - Montseny, Federica. Printed writings, printed interview, speeches, and printed excerpts, 1936-1981 (Folder 8)
  - Moron, Gabriel. Printed writings and typescript statement, 1937-1942 (Folder 9)
  - Morrow, Felix. Printed writings, 1938 (Folder 10)
  - Nelken de Paul, Margarita. Interview notes, 1939-1940 (Folder 11)
  - Orr, Lois Cusick. Typescript copy of "The Anarchist Millenium: Memories of the Spanish Revolution, " (incomplete), n.d., 1936-1937 (Folder 12)
  - Orwell, George. Printed writings, clippings, and articles by Herbert L. Matthews and others, 1937-1971 (Folder 13)
  - Peirats, Jose. Printed interview, writings, and articles by others, 1951-1980 (Folder 14)
  - Peiro, Juan. Printed writings, clippings, and notes, 1938-1979 (Folder 15)
  - Pozas, Sebastian. Typescript interview and notes, 1939 (Folder 16)
  - Prat, Jose. Printed interview and clipping, 1974-1979 (Folder 17)
  - Prieto, Indalecio. Printed writings, speech, notes, and printed articles by others, 1940-1981 (Folder 18)
  - Quintana y Peia, Alfonso. Typescript writings, SEE ALSO: SPANISH CIVIL WAR SUBJECT FILE/Casares Quiroga, Santiago, 1977-1981. (Folder 19)
  - Renn, Ludwig. Shorthand interview notes and typescript (Folder 20)
  - Rocker, Rudolf. Printed writings, 1938 (Folder 21)
  - Rojo, Vicente. Printed writings, printed excerpts, clippings, and notes, 1939-1967 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Rosal, Amaro del. Printed writings, 1949 (Folder 2)
  - Rudiger, Helmut. Printed writing and typescript reports (incomplete), 1937-1940 (Folder 3)
  - Sanchez Roman, Felipe. Typescript interview notes, 1940 (Folder 4)
  - Schwartzmann, Manuel. Notes and typescript copies of "L'Industrie de Guerre de la Republique Espagnole," "La Naissance et l'Activite de la D.E.C.A. en Espagne," and "Somosierra," (Folder 5)
  - Siqueiros, David Alfaro. Shorthand interview notes and typescript photocopy of "David Alfaro Siqueiros Habla de la Revolucion Mexicana,", 1937-1940 (Folder 6)
  - Soria, Georges. Printed writings and printed article, 1976-1978 (Folder 7)
  - Souchy, Agustin. Printed writings and notes, 1937-1946 (Folder 8)
  - Tarradellas, Josep. Printed interviews, printed writings, and clippings, 1937-1986 (Folder 9)
  - Torre, Matilda de la. Typescript interview notes, 1937 (Folder 10)
  - Toryho, Jacinto. Printed writings, ca. 1938-1975 (Folder 11)
  - Trejo, Blanca Lydia. Printed writing, n.d. (Folder 12)
  - Ulibarri, Mariano Gamir. Printed writing and clipping, 1936-1939 (Folder 13)
  - Vidarte, Juan-Simeon. Printed writing, 1973 (Folder 14)
  - Weil, Simone. Includes material relating to Weil's correspondence with Georges Bernanos. Printed writings, clipping, biographical sketch, and printed article about Bernanos, 1939-1980 (Folder 15)
  - Zugazagoitia, Julian. Printed writings, 1940-1977 (Folder 16)
- CLIPPINGS, 1934-1976. (Box 15-82)
  Arranged alphabetically by serial title and chronologically thereunder. See also: SCRAPBOOKS and MICROFILM
  - General
    - General
      - Official
        - 1936 May-1939 February 25 (Box 15, Folder 1-6)
        - 1939 February 26-March 27 (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - International
        - General, 1936-1939 (Folder 2)
        - France, 1936-1943 (Folder 3-4)
        - Great Britain
          - 1936-1937 (Folder 5)
          - 1938-1939 (Box 17, Folder 1)
        - Latin America, 1937-1939 (Folder 2)
        - United States
          - General, 1936-1939 (Folder 3-4)
          - Cultura Proletaria, 1936-1942 (Folder 5)
          - Spanish Revolution, 1937 (Folder 6)
    - Chronological. NOTE: Most of this material reflects a prior chronological arrangement which includes many of the same publications itemized subsequently
      - General. Fragments (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - 1934 June 1-1935 November 28 (Folder 2)
      - 1936 March 3-July 23 (Folder 3-8)
      - 1936 July 24-August 2 (Box 19, Folder 1-8)
      - 1936 August 3-12 (Box 20, Folder 1-6)
      - 1936 August 13-24 (Box 21, Folder 1-6)
      - 1936 August 25-September 10 (Box 22, Folder 1-10)
      - 1936 September 11-30 (Box 23, Folder 1-10)
      - 1936 October 1-21 (Box 24, Folder 1-11)
      - 1936 October 22-November 10 (Box 25, Folder 1-10)
      - 1936 November 11-30 (Box 26, Folder 1-9)
      - 1936 December 1-19 (Box 27, Folder 1-9)
      - 1936 December 20-1937 January 8 (Box 28, Folder 1-10)
      - 1937 January 9-26 (Box 29, Folder 1-9)
      - 1937 January 27-February 12 (Box 30, Folder 1-8)
      - 1937 February 13-28 (Box 31, Folder 1-8)
      - 1937 March 1-14 (Box 32, Folder 1-7)
      - 1937 March 15-30 (Box 33, Folder 1-8)
      - 1937 March 31-April 14 (Box 34, Folder 1-8)
      - 1937 April 15-26 (Box 35, Folder 1-6)
      - 1937 April 27-May 4 (Box 36, Folder 1-7)
      - 1937 May 5-19 (Box 37, Folder 1-8)
      - 1937 May 20-June 4 (Box 38, Folder 1-8)
      - 1937 June 5-24 (Box 39, Folder 1-10)
      - 1937 June 25-July 13 (Box 40, Folder 1-10)
      - 1937 July 14-August 2 (Box 41, Folder 1-10)
      - 1937 August 3-26 (Box 42, Folder 1-12)
      - 1937 August 27-September 16 (Box 43, Folder 1-10)